All right. Good morning, Canvas Church. How is everybody? All right. That was all right.
That was okay. I'll take that. I'll take that. Second service when we had one was usually
the really loud service because everybody was awake. They had their coffee, so a little
more coffee. I've got coffee right over here if you need some. In case you don't know me,
my name is Dave Ballinger. I'm one of the elders here at Canvas Church, and I have the honor
to preach to you today and bring the message today. Before we dive into the message, and
I'm really not sure how long we will be here. This could be 15 minutes or this could be two
hours and 15 minutes. Settle in. We'll see how it goes. Let the Spirit lead us where it
will. I wanted to just acknowledge somebody and embarrass them. I know they'll be embarrassed
by this, but I just want to acknowledge Dave Calhoun. Dave, in case you don't know, is very
behind the scenes. He handles our AV. He's done it for over eight years at Canvas. Our live
streams. He handles the slides. He's also responsible for the live stream that's going on in the other
service. So I just want to thank Dave. Dave is the guy who, when everything is going right,
you have no idea he exists. And when everything is going wrong, everybody's looking at him. So
that's Dave right there with the headphones on.
I felt compelled when I was sending Dave my Scripture verses that needed to be on the screen last night,
I don't know, probably later than they should be delivered, to say, man, he's been doing this so long
and he probably gets me Scripture verses like the morning of and at 1230 at night and all kinds
of times of weird requests. So props to Dave. Thank you, Dave, for all your years serving on Canvas.
I also want to thank the rest of our volunteers. As you know, church requires a lot of hands and feet
to do what we do. And we have just a tremendous amount of volunteers. So I just want to thank all
the other volunteers. Maybe I'll get to you guys later, if I have another opportunity, if they don't drag me off the stage here.
And speaking of serving, this kind of connects with my message today.
If you're not serving, that's okay. If you're new to church and you're not serving, that's okay.
If you're a seasoned vet, God has given you gifts. God has given you tremendous gifts to serve the community,
to serve the church in one way or the other. And I would encourage you, not shame you, but I would encourage you
to see if there is an area where you could serve. Maybe it's not a church. Maybe it's in your community.
Maybe it's somewhere in our community. But serve. Give of your time. Give of your resources.
Give of the gifts that God has given you. It is one of the best ways to get connected at church and in your community
and build community. So I just wanted to encourage you with that.
Let's see. So speaking of gifts, I have a few that I just kind of want to brag about before we dive into the message today.
One of them is I get the opportunity to preach to you guys today.
Second, and probably one of the greatest gifts that I've ever been blessed with is my son, Aaron,
came to faith in Jesus two weeks ago.
So if you're a parent out there and you've been praying for your kids for years to come to know Jesus
and put their faith in him, you know what a tremendous blessing that is
and how humbled I am that that happened.
I also am celebrating my 23-year wedding anniversary today with my wonderful wife.
She's sitting right there.
She's New Ballinger.
It's ironic. She's like, you're preaching on our anniversary?
I was like, yeah, isn't it awesome?
It's going to be great, right?
I gave you a shout-out. It's going to be great.
So God's been so good to me.
I just wanted to give him praise and glory for the 23 years of marriage that, you know,
I've done my fair amount of share of trying to undermine, and God's correct me and put me back on track.
So I'm blessed to have my family.
I'm blessed to have my wife of 23 years.
And so it's funny, I was looking online for what do you get your wife for a 23-year wedding anniversary,
and, you know, I'm Googling, and, you know, I'm getting a bunch of weird sites to come up.
And to my joy, what I found out is there really is no actual traditional gift for 23 years.
Once you get to 20, it's like it goes right to 25, and that's silver.
Now, you could go, like, to the U.K., and there's some weird ones that come up.
I'm getting a scowl right now for my life.
So there is not actually – so 20 to 25 is what it's supposed to say.
I'm going to have to make up for this big time later.
So just so you know, I'm just digging myself deeper and deeper, so go with me.
So 20 is China.
A lot of ladies in the room probably know that.
Probably most of the guys don't.
25 is silver.
Just a heads up, fellas.
What I did find that was interesting, there was one site that said a 23-year wedding anniversary gift would be air.
And that's the one I went with.
There was a bunch of ones that you could plug in, and I went, air.
She's got overabundance, obviously, of air.
I should probably stop while I'm in the hay.
All right.
So I beat that horse to death.
Thank you for bearing with me through that, guys.
Love you too, baby.
All right.
So if you have been here over the last – what has it been?
Eight weeks or so, I'm guesstimating.
We are wrapping up the series in James.
Some of you are probably like, finally.
You guys will be preaching through James forever.
It seems like some of you may have really enjoyed going through an entire book of the Bible.
I'm in the latter group.
I love kind of going from the start of the book to the end of a book versus kind of jumping around and doing topical.
Topical is good, too.
But this is our last sermon series of James, so I will do my best to honor that.
For you note-takers, this is your time to take notes, because once I actually get into my sermon, you probably won't deal with it anyway.
It's probably not going to do it.
So the book of James was written around 50 to 60 A.D., okay?
And it's possibly one of the oldest New Testament writings.
That or Galatians, all right?
Subject to debate.
Hot debate, which was contested somewhere in some coffee shop.
So the James that wrote the book of James is the half-brother of Jesus, okay?
I think Ryan has mentioned that in the past.
This is not the Apostle James that's writing this book, okay?
So the Apostle James and his brother John were the sons of Zebedee.
They're talked about in Mark 1 and a bunch of other areas of the apostles.
They were also known as the sons of thunder, okay?
And if you're interested in how they got that interesting name, sons of thunder, I think that's pretty cool.
Look in Luke 9.
I'll just give you a quick little summary there.
They're walking through Samaria, and they felt that some people had disrespected Jesus,
so they asked him if they could call down fire from heaven and just, like, burn everybody up, right?
And Jesus gives them the name of the sons of thunder.
So it's pretty awesome.
Can you relate, right?
There's a lot of relatable things that the disciples and apostles do, or the disciples do that I can relate.
If I don't have to call down fire from heaven, I don't have to do that.
Especially driving to work.
Also, Matthew 13, 55 lists James as one of four brothers of Jesus.
Interesting fact.
James was also the leader of the Jerusalem Council.
Let's read about that in Acts 15.
Also, an interesting fact that Ryan's mentioned is Jesus' brothers didn't initially believe in him.
They didn't believe he was who he claimed to be.
In John 7, it says that Jesus was staying out of Judea purposefully because the Jews there were trying to take his life.
So, sarcastically, this is the tone I need to read this in.
Jesus' brothers say to him, this is John 7, 3-5,
Leave here and go to Judea where your followers can see your miracles.
Does that sound sarcastic?
You can't become famous if you hide here like this.
If you can do such wonderful things, show yourself to the world.
Well, brotherly jealousy.
For even his brothers didn't believe in him.
It's not a hard stretch to think that your brother doesn't believe that you're the Messiah.
Right?
Okay, probably like, no, you're like my brother.
You know, coming out with you and we grew up together.
You're obviously not the Messiah.
Any of us in here with siblings can probably relate to that sentiment.
Interestingly, after Jesus' resurrection, 1 Corinthians 15, 7 says that Jesus appeared to James.
He was one of the people that Jesus appeared to directly.
After his resurrection.
And finally, James was martyred for his faith in 62 AD.
He was stoned to death by the Jews.
I had to look that up.
I wasn't exactly sure how James died.
I was pretty sure that he was martyred.
As I was reading that, I found it highly ironic after reading the Jesus' brother's sarcastic call to have him go to Judea,
where Jesus was staying out of because he thought, you know, he knew that the Jews were trying to kill him,
that he winds up dying for his faith and believing in his brother.
There are a lot of strong examples that we can turn to in the Bible for people's faith turning, their understanding turning, their eyes being open.
James is one of them.
He went from mocking his brother to dying for him because he believed in who he says he was finally.
So I just wanted to read you with that.
I just want to wrap this introduction up here and just say it's I personally feel, I hope you guys do too,
that it has been a tremendous blessing to sit and listen to the various people come up and preach through the book of James
and hear everyone's perspectives.
Ryan's preached through it.
Corey has preached through it.
Andy's preached through it.
We've had Joel here.
Michelle has preached.
And I love not only going through the book, you know, beginning to end,
but I also love hearing all the different angles and perspectives
and how God talks to individual people to bring a different perspective to the message.
So to me, it's been just a huge blessing.
So I guess I just have a little point that I wanted to make here before we pray.
And it's about Bible study.
It's about reading your Bible.
I've said a couple times that I'm a big fan of reading the book, reading books from chapter 1 to chapter 10.
And because I'm not a fan necessarily of the verse of the day,
so if you're a new believer or you're a seasoned believer who maybe hasn't studied the Bible a lot,
you've gone to church a lot, I would just like to recommend if you're going to be in the Word,
I'm sorry, when you're in the Word, that's my trying to help you there.
Don't rely on the verse of the day to kind of get you through and fully comprehend and try to understand what God is saying.
There's a lot of context that's missed in the verse of the day.
They're great if you understand context of the verse that's coming on it.
But I think it's much more valuable.
You get a lot more context when you do a Bible study and you read an entire book.
Maybe pick a chapter a day.
We just started the book of Mark at my house with my wife and my son, and that was great.
We're going to go through from beginning to end.
So that's just my, that's Dave's opinion.
You can just take that and do whatever you want with it.
All right, now let's actually start doing some Bible study.
So let's turn to, if you have your Bibles or if you have your phones, James 5, verses 19 to 20.
James 5, 19 to 20 says,
Dear Heavenly Father, God, thank you for providing a place for us to meet today, God.
Thank you for working all things out so we can be here.
God, help us to put aside the distractions of life.
God, there is so much going on in each and every single person's life that is here.
Good things and bad things, God.
Busy things.
God, I pray that you help us clear those distractions from our hearts and from our minds.
Help us to listen to you and hear from the Spirit, God,
on what you want us to take individually out of this message.
God, I pray that it's not me speaking, but you.
I pray for your help today as I go through this message.
And let it bring you glory and honor, because when you get glory and honor, it's very good.
In Jesus' name, amen.
Amen. All right. There is so much. It's funny. I've preached twice in James and both times Ryan's like, hey, here's the verses you get. I'm like, sweet. What is it? It's like a whole chapter? Because I can like burn 15 minutes just reading through a chapter, right? He's like, no, it's two verses. I'm like, awesome. How am I going to get up here and talk? Obviously, you guys are probably like, you can do it. He's already talked a lot already.
Through two verses. There is literally so much in these two verses. We could probably just do a three-week Bible study just on James 5, 19 and 20. I will try not to do that. I want to focus on two areas here. Wandering believers and then the people who God uses to bring them back.
So let's start with the wandering believers. When James says, my dear brothers and sisters, if someone among you, okay, so trying to highlight a few of these words here, James is talking about people who profess to be Christians.
People who profess to have faith in Christ. They've given their life to Jesus. They're going to church. They're reading their Bibles or their scrolls, whatever they have been.
So this is the context of who, that we're talking about here. It's believers.
And when he says wanders from the truth, in the context of how James is saying this, I don't think that he's saying, he's saying that this is kind of happening, not necessarily happening deliberately.
This isn't a deliberate wander. Well, you don't deliberately wander, do you? I don't think you do. Maybe some of you do, but most of us don't deliberately wander.
Sure, we just kind of wander off, right? You're going, oh, how do I get over here, right?
This isn't a turning your back to God, walking away, and, you know, I never believed. It's not that that he's doing here.
He's talking about people who are believers, put their faith in Jesus, said they did, kind of taking their eyes off the ball,
taking their eyes off Jesus, and finding that they've wandered away from their faith or from truth.
James also says that these people that wander away, the sinners that wander away, can be saved from death,
and that they can bring about forgiveness of many sins.
So there is danger in wandering away, okay?
As we wander, as we wander, or if we wander, we can become more disconnected from Christ the longer that we wander,
the longer that, you know, we're not plugged into what Jesus is saying in our lives.
We're not seeking him. We're not in prayer.
More disconnected can lead us further and further away
and can undermine how we're called to walk, right?
How we're called to live.
And even sometimes it can infiltrate some of the things that we think are absolute truth.
We can start to maybe get some different opinions on that.
So I think there's two ways that we can wander.
One of them is doctrinally.
We can wander away from the truth.
You know, there's non-negotiables when it comes to the gospel.
We can't get to heaven through our own goodness, right?
Baptism doesn't save you.
It's all through Jesus that we get saved.
When we doctrinally start to loosen our principles,
some of those things maybe we can start to question.
And we can start to listen to other voices or other people and say,
oh, no, you need to be circumcised and saved, right?
Maybe not now, right?
I'm using an early church passage that was being taught
that you needed something in Jesus in order to be saved
or baptism in Jesus in order to be saved
or anything in Jesus to be saved, right?
You need to tithe and have Jesus in order to be saved.
Any of those things are wrong.
We need Jesus.
None of our works save us.
Our own goodness doesn't save us.
How many times we go to church doesn't save us, right?
So doctrinally, we can kind of get off base.
Also, and probably much more quickly, behaviorally, we can wander from truth, right?
So living for ourselves instead of God,
indulging in sinful desires,
not staying connected,
not going to church,
all kinds of stuff,
we can behaviorally start to change
when we aren't abiding in Christ
or walking away from the truth.
Last Sunday,
Ryan said,
sometimes we feel confident
in our walk or, you know,
in our relationship with Christ.
I'm paraphrasing there.
And other weeks,
we struggle to conform our lives to follow Jesus.
If anybody's been a follower of Jesus
longer than, like, 15 minutes,
they will know that this statement is true.
We don't follow Jesus perfectly.
We're prone to wander away,
all of us, right?
If you're not prone to wander,
let me know.
I'll talk to you after church
and we'll go through some stuff.
But we're prone to wander.
We're prone to have these moments
where we feel like,
man, I'm so close with God
and I'm rocking it
and I'm in my Bible
and I'm just filled with the Spirit
and I'm being obedient
and there's other times
where it's like,
but I'm on vacation
and, you know,
that these margaritas are delicious
and put whatever else
that you want in there,
whatever slippery slope
that you found yourself going down.
I'm speaking just for myself,
by the way.
I'm sure none of you guys do that.
We can have this
type of relationship
in our lives.
In many cases,
it's because we've allowed ourselves
to become distracted
from our relationship,
from our connection to Jesus.
A lot of times,
these distractions can be, like,
super nefarious
and when I say super nefarious,
they can be things like,
we think are good,
like, I'm really busy at work.
Man, my kids have a lot of sporting events
going on.
I've got taxes I have to do,
buying a house,
no vacations after that,
and these good things,
these lessons,
can start to,
if we don't prioritize them properly,
they can take over
so much of our time.
They can add worry to us, right?
Now, I have to get this done.
Like, well,
I've got to get my Bible
because I've got to get
these taxes in.
So, even seemingly good things
that we've been blessed with
can take us away
from our walk
and cause us
to wander away.
It can cause this
change of position
that we feel
in our relationship
with Christ.
Sometimes,
if we're not careful,
these things can go on
for not just weeks,
days, weeks,
but they can go for months
and possibly even years
if we're not careful.
That's the danger
of wandering away
from our connection
to Christ.
So,
Scripture has a lot of terms
for followers of Christ,
and a lot of them
are super awesome.
disciples.
I'm a disciple.
Okay, that sounds cool,
I guess.
If you're a Christian,
that definitely sounds cool.
If you're not a Christian,
it might sound very religious.
Brothers.
Brothers in Christ.
How about elect?
I mean, I'm elect.
The Bible calls me elect.
If I'm in Christ,
if I'm saved,
I'm elect.
How about a saint?
Sounded pretty good.
We are also
probably better known
as sheep.
Jesus calls us sheep.
It's not a very
flattering description,
right?
Like,
that sounded kind of cool,
you know.
Disciple,
I'm more with that
now that I am a sheep.
Disciple actually
sounds better.
I'm not feeling
a sheep too much.
In John chapter 10,
verse 11,
Jesus says that
I am the good shepherd.
The good shepherd
sacrifices his life
for his sheep.
In John 10, 27,
Jesus also says,
my sheep,
listen to my voice.
I know them
and they follow me.
Hebrews 13,
20 to 21
says,
now may the God
of peace
who through the blood
of eternal covenant
brought back
from the dead
for our Lord Jesus,
that great shepherd
of the sheep,
equip you
with everything good
for doing his will
and may he work
in us
what is pleasing
to him
through Jesus Christ
to whom be the glory
for ever and ever.
Amen.
Got some interesting
facts about sheep.
I know this is why
you guys came here.
I'm fulfilling your desires.
We're going to read
about sheep a little bit.
Sheep,
if they sense danger,
some characteristics.
If there are any people
that raise sheep in here,
I'm not at least
one or two people
that you do.
You can probably
confirm this.
If they sense danger,
it can cause them
to run blindly away
to avoid
what's frightening them.
Sheep may stray
by following
other sheep.
or because they're
not paying attention
while they're grazing.
Sheep may also stray
to satisfy curiosity.
Doing my research,
I found an article
that you can put this up
from Savvy Farm Life.
Why do sheep stray?
Most of us understand
goats to be
especially curious creatures
getting into all sorts
of trouble
to investigate anything
that may strike their fancy.
Though this tends
to be true
for the nature of goats,
sheep are not immune
to letting curiosity
get the best of them either.
A sheep that is
safely tucked
into the flock
may seem an interesting
or seemingly
unfreatening object
and might wander away
from the flock
to investigate further.
Distracted with
its investigation,
he may end up
separating himself
from the flock
and wandering off.
Eventually,
he will discover
the error
and become stressed
calling out
to the flock
until he finds
his way back.
Also,
during my research,
I found this really
poignant gift
that some of you guys
have maybe seen this.
This is someone
saving a sheep
from a ditch
that it fell in,
right?
And the sheep
is so happy
it just can't,
it's just...
And he's right back
in the ditch.
I just thought
that was...
First,
you know,
you think that's hysterical,
that's,
oh my gosh,
I can't believe it,
how ironic is that?
And then the more
you kind of look at that
and you kind of parallel
this to what can be
our walk
following Christ
sometimes,
there can be
a lot of similarities,
right?
I don't know
about you guys,
if you ever
prayed the prayer,
God,
if you get me
out of this one,
I will never
fill in the blank.
And then like,
two months later,
you're like,
God,
I know I said
I wasn't going
to do it,
but I did it again
so you can get me
out of here.
I went back
in the ditch.
And maybe I'm
a slightly less humorous
though,
maybe we struggle
with our own
shortcomings,
we struggle with
sin and desires,
and we give in
to our desires
and we feel shamed
and we say,
God,
I can't stop
doing whatever,
dot,
dot.
Help me to
stop doing
this.
Weeks and
weeks go by
and you find
yourself back
in the same
ditch again.
You go,
why God,
why can't I
overcome this
thing in my
life?
I hate it,
I don't want
it,
but I can't
seem to make
it go away
completely.
This is what I
think of when I
see the sheep
falling into the
ditch right after
it's been rescued.
John warns us
about idols.
When we
prioritize
things in our
life above
God,
it's called
idolatry.
like the
things that
I was talking
about,
good job,
your job,
your family,
relationships,
all these good
things,
if they take
a priority
over our
relationship with
God,
they can get
in the way.
And if we
continue to
focus on them
and pour our
energy into
them and our
focus on them,
they can become
idols.
And idols are
things that
take us far
away from
God because
idols are the
things that
have our
hearts and
not God.
When I was
younger,
I remember
reading a story
in Exodus
about the
golden calf.
And I
would grow up
as a Christian
and read the
Bible More
and I'd hear
about idolatry
and I'm like,
got that one
in the bag.
I don't know,
you never
worshipped an
idol.
Golden calf,
that's ridiculous.
That,
you know,
as God
has taught
me,
idols are
way more
sinister than
a golden calf.
They're the
things all
around me in
my life
vying for
my attention
and they
can be
idols if
I allow
them to
be without
putting them
in their
proper
perspective
to God.
Ironically,
Jill read
Luke 15,
1-7,
and that's
part of my
message today.
So I don't know
if Ryan told her
that was in
there or that's
just the Holy
Spirit working,
but we're
going to put
that up.
Tax collectors
and other
notorious sinners
often came to
listen to Jesus
teach.
By the way,
Jill will have
done this much
better than I
did.
This made the
Pharisees and
the teachers
of the religious
law complain
that he was
associating with
such a sinful
people, even
eating with
them.
So Jesus
told them a
story.
If a man
had a hundred
sheep and
one of them
got lost,
what would
he do?
Won't he
leave the 99
others in the
wilderness to
go to search
for the one
that is lost
until he
finds it?
And when he
found it, he
will joyfully
carry it home
on his shoulders.
And when he
arrives, he
will call
together his
friends and
neighbors, saying
rejoice with
me because I
have found my
lost sheep.
In the same
way, there is
more joy in
heaven over one
lost sinner who
repents and
returns to God
other than
99 others who
are righteous and
have not strayed
away.
This shows the
character of
Christ.
That he does
that he's not
surprised if we
wander.
And he will
leave the flock
to come and
get us.
That's his
heart for us.
He loves us.
I use this
analogy here
because God
uses people
to not only
spread the
gospel, to
use us, to
invite us in
to spread the
gospel, to
share our faith,
but also to
be used as
instruments for
his glory for
when there are
believers who
wander.
he can use
other believers
to bring
them back.
So, if you
can put up
James 5, 19
to 20 again.
We kind of
framed out the
dear brothers and
sisters of
someone among
you wanders
away from the
truth that is
brought back.
We kind of put
brackets around
that and said
James is
talking about
believers who
have wandered.
In verse 20,
he says that
you can be
sure that
whoever brings
the sinner
back will
save that
person from
the death
and bring
about forgiveness
of many sins.
That whoever
is also a
believer.
So, both of
the people in
this story are
believers.
God uses his
flock or his
community or his
church, his
people to
perform many
times and act
like this to
bring a wandering
brother back.
This is what we
talk about when we
talk about the
priesthood of all
believers at
campus.
If you've been
around our
church for any
amount of
time, you
will have heard
us talk about
the priesthood of
all believers.
If you've been
around church in
general for any
amount of time,
you may have a
fallacy or a
misconception that
the pastors up
front are the
ones who are
supposed to be
doing God's
work, and the
people in the
seats are the
ones who are
supposed to root
the pastors on.
That's just
completely not
how it's
supposed to
be.
We are all
called to
participate in
working for the
kingdom, whether
it's sharing the
gospel or finding
lost brothers.
We all have a
responsibility.
This is the
priesthood of all
believers that we
talk about so
much here at
campus, about
breaking the
stigma that it's
just pastors to
do the work,
that it's all of
us to do the
work.
There's really
no great
distinction between
pastors and
other believers,
right?
We all are
called to
participate in
sharing the
gospel and
sharing our
faith and
loving one
another and
exhorting one
another.
So this
ties directly
into the
whoever James
is talking
about.
This is why
Christian
community is
so important.
as a flock
we're supposed
to be looking
out for each
other.
We should be
having
relationships.
We should be
purposely building
relationships in
our lives.
We should be
reaching out to
others to build
relationships.
So if and when
that person needs
somebody, they have
a community that
they can go to,
someone that they
might trust or
someone that
will, if they
don't know they're
wandering, will
say, hey, is
everything all
right?
I noticed we
weren't in church
for the last
little while.
Hey, how are you
doing?
You don't, and
everything doesn't
seem okay.
It's something that
you want to talk
about.
I hear Christians
say, and you
probably heard it
too, they don't
need to go to
church, right?
I don't need to
go to church.
Me and God, we
got to have an
agreement.
I read my Bible
out in the yard
on the stump and
don't need church.
Church is far.
I got to get up
early, whatever your
excuses.
Those are mine, by
the way, getting up
early.
I don't want to do
that.
We all need to be
together.
We're not meant
to do our walk
alone.
That's kind of why
we're called a flock.
That's why Jesus
calls us, not only
because we wander as
sheep, but because
we're his flock,
right?
We should be looking
out for one another,
living life together,
doing life together.
This is what a
Christian experience
should look like.
For so many years,
this was not my
story.
I would go to
church on Sunday,
check the box,
come home,
work, groan
because it was
Saturday night.
I got to get up
early for church.
I went to church
again and couldn't
wait to get out
of there.
I was doing it all
wrong for all the
wrong reasons.
I said earlier at the
beginning of the
message that one of
the things that kind
of changed my
experience was serving
in church and, oh
my gosh, getting to
know people and
know names and talk
to people and build
relationships and hear
their stories.
and have them speak
into my life and
have an opportunity
to speak into
somebody else's
life.
Serving changed a
lot in my personal
life.
So I want to go
back to that.
If you're not in
community, if you're
not serving, if you're
not connecting, I urge
you to try or try
again to do that.
It will put you in
the flock, which is
where you are meant
to be, in your
community, not
wandering by yourself
with no one who
knows you well to
come to your rescue
if you do wander.
I want to talk to
we're going to go
focus on the
whoever again.
So the whoever
part of this
passage in verse 20.
who brings the
wanderer back, that
person.
What's our
motivation?
What should be our
motivation for
having an
uncomfortable
conversation?
Hey, I haven't
seen you in church
in a few weeks.
Everybody wants to
do that, right?
Hey, something
might not seem
right.
Are you okay?
What should be our
motivation?
Our motivation
should always be
love and
compassion for
the person.
If you feel
called, I see
Bob.
Bob ain't been
at church.
He's been at the
bar.
I don't know why
I just had an
accent like that,
but it just
seemed to fit.
We should check
our hearts before
we go to
somebody to
bring them
back, right?
I want to read
this passage from
John.
Jesus gives us
an amazing
example of
showing compassion
and love to
somebody who
was caught
in sin.
So, Jesus
will model this
way better than
any analogy I
can give you.
John 8,
verses 2-11
says,
But early the
next morning,
he was back
at the temple.
A crowd soon
gathered, and he
sat down and
taught them.
He was speaking
when the
teachers of the
law and the
Pharisees brought
a woman who
had been caught
in the act of
adultery, and
they put her in
front of the
crowd.
Where's the
guy, first
of all?
He wasn't
drugged in
there.
Sorry, that
was just a
thought bubble.
So, they
bring this
woman who
was caught
in the act
of adultery.
That's like,
if Jesus is at
the temple,
that's like,
hey, we're at
church on
Sunday, like
right now, and
a bunch of
dudes drag
this woman in
who's caught
in the act
of adultery,
and brings
her in front
of the church
and shames
her, and
they're doing
this.
Let's read.
So, they put
her in front of
the crowd.
Can you even
comprehend this
happening right
now?
They say,
teacher, they
said to Jesus,
this woman was
caught in the
act of
adultery.
The law of
Moses says to
stone her.
So, she was
supposed to be
killed, according
to the law of
Moses.
They asked him,
what do you
say?
They were
trying to trap
him in the
things, something
that they could
use against
him, but
Jesus stooped
down and wrote
in the dust
with his
finger.
Nobody knows
what Jesus
wrote, by the
way.
They kept
demanding an
answer, so he
stood up again
and said,
all right, but
let the one who
has never
sinned, cast
the first stone.
And he
stooped down
again and he
wrote in the
dust.
Again, nobody
knows what
he wrote.
Maybe those
guys did.
When the
accusers heard
this, they
slipped away
one by one,
beginning with
the oldest,
and told only
Jesus was left
in the middle
of the crowd
with the
woman.
Then Jesus
stood up again
and said to
the woman,
where are
your accusers?
Don't even
one of them
condemn you.
No, Lord,
she said.
And Jesus
said, neither
do I.
Go and
sin no more.
So they're
trying to set
Jesus up,
and Jesus
shows them
all up because
he's God in
the flesh.
He says, if
you have sin,
if you don't
have sin, you
can't cast the
first stone.
Go for it.
It's ironic that
they start with
the oldest guy
and they
walk away.
Jesus shows
compassion to
this woman.
He didn't
excuse her
sin.
He didn't
say, you
know, hey,
go on back
and do what
you were
doing.
He said,
don't sin
anymore.
Because he
knew that
the problems
and the
trials and
the shame
it was
bringing into
her life.
But he
didn't
focus on
that.
He focused
on being
compassionate
to her.
It was
this compassion
that just
comes off
the page
here for
her.
John 3.16
says,
for God
so loved
the world
that he
gave his
one and
only son
that anyone
who believes
in him
will not
perish
without
eternal
life.
And that's
like on
every coffee
mug on
the planet,
right?
Or a lot
of them.
But what
never makes
the coffee
mug is
John 3.17
which says
God sent
his son
into the
world not
to judge
the world
but to
save the
world
through him.
We see
the character
of God
play out
in the
mercy that
he shows
for us
by sending
Jesus
to be
the sacrifice
for our
sins.
We show
Jesus,
we see
Jesus'
compassion
for this
woman
when he
doesn't
accuse
her
of the
sin
that she
was
caught
right
handed.
And this
should be
the model
for our
motivation
if we
feel compelled
to go to
someone who
we think is
wandering and
bring them
back.
I would
suggest
before you
go and
you feel
compelled
that you
pray.
Pray for
the person
first.
Just don't
jump right
in.
Pray while
you're together
and pray for
them after
you go.
Ask God
to help
you.
Because with
the wrong
intentions,
we can
do a lot
more harm
than good
if we
come
accusing
people
and not
with the
heart of
love and
compassion
who have
wandered
away.
Romans 12,
1, 3
says,
Be honest
with ourselves
lest we
think we
are better
than we
are.
The person
who may
be
wandering,
we've
all
experienced
the same
thing that
they have.
And if
you haven't,
you're
blessed.
And just
wait.
Matthew 7,
3, 5,
Jesus says,
Why do you
look at the
speck of
skulldust
in your
brother's
eye and
pay no
attention to
the plank
in your
own eye?
We have
been greatly
forgiven.
We are no
better and
no more
righteous than
anyone else.
Only God
is good.
Which is
why we
point whoever
that wanderer
is back to
him.
Because only
through Jesus
can we be
healed,
forgiven,
can we be
made right,
redeemed,
and can we
be restored.
God bless you
and I'm
running a
little
long,
but I
want to
just take
this time
to say
that this
is also
an opportunity
to possibly
share a
testimony.
Your
testimony,
if you
don't know,
is your
confession of
what God
has brought
you through
in your
life.
in any
of you
with a
testimony
that God
has walked
you through
a trial,
a problem,
you will
be much
more sensitive
to other
people going
through those
similar trials.
I personally
believe it's a
sin not to
share your
testimony when
you see
somebody else
who's
struggling,
who you
know,
love,
and not
share how
God brought
you through,
to encourage
them, to
turn them
back to
Him.
our
testimonies
are
powerful,
our
testimonies
can bring
people back
to God,
but our
testimonies
are useless
if we do
not share
them, and
we don't
know people
with whom
we can
share them,
who we
don't feel
comfortable
sharing,
we haven't
built relations
with to
share them.
So if
you're here
and you're
wandering,
I'm sure
there is a
small voice
in your
heart
that you're
hearing right
now.
It's saying
you're far
from me.
Come back.
My prayer
for you
today is
to listen
to the
words.
Humble
yourself.
Ask God
for help.
Give in
to Him.
Return
He loves
you deeply
and shows
you and
shows us
great
compassion.
James 4
8 says
in the
ESV,
draw near
to God
and He
will draw
near to
you.
Jesus
also says
knock.
Seek and
you'll find
knock and
the door
will be
open.
Seek
God.
Return
to God.
Find a
brother,
someone that
you trust
in Christ.
I hope
you have
that person.
confess to
them
what you're
dealing with.
This isn't
an open,
don't put
that on
Facebook,
don't just
pick somebody
out of the
crowd and
start confessing
your sins.
I would
never
recommend
that.
Find
somebody
that you
trust
and share
what you're
struggling with.
And if
you're still
not confident
to do
that,
just ask
them to
pray for
you.
Typically,
this will
be the
time where
we take
communion.
But I
felt compelled
last night to
add more
onto this
message.
think about
that part
of the
verse
where
it says
that when
we turn
a sinner
back to
the truth,
it covers
a multitude
of sins.
But I
want to
say in a
sobering
way that
there is
no covering
for sin
outside of
Jesus.
And that
is a
very
sobering
thought.
One day,
the Bible
says,
as Jesus
we will
all stand
before a
holy,
righteous,
and just
God and
give an
account for
our lives.
If the
thought of
standing in
front of a
holy and
righteous and
just God
gives you
anxiety and
fear,
it's good
because you're
in the
right place.
Proverbs
9, 10
says,
the fear
of the
Lord is
the beginning
of wisdom.
Your fear
is a
warning sign
that says,
if I get
to that
point,
there is
no way
I will
be justified
with my
good works,
with how
good I
am.
The things
that I've
done and
the things
that I've
said,
I know
that I'm
guilty in
front of
a perfect
and holy
and righteous
God.
But there
is good
news.
That same
holy,
just,
and righteous
God
is just,
it's filled
with just
as much
grace and
mercy and
love.
And he
exists,
he's given
us example
after example,
time after
time,
and the
ultimate
example that
he showed
us was
that he
sent his
only son
to live
sinlessly
and be
the sacrifice
for our
sin
and rose
him again.
He values
you individually
so much
that he
would send
Jesus to
suffer and
die on the
cross because
he knew
that the
penalty
for sin
would have
to be
paid.
And he
chose to
sacrifice
his son
to take
that penalty.
So if
you're here
today and you
don't have a
relationship
with Jesus,
if you
aren't confident
that you
will be in
heaven
because of
Jesus covering
for you
and you're
standing alone,
I want to
tell you that
the offer
for God's
mercy and
grace is
wide open
to you.
Romans 10
9 says,
if we
confess with
our mouth
and believe
in our
heart that
Jesus is
Lord,
we will
be saved.
Some of
you may
not know
that.
Some of
you may
not be
comfortable
with that.
I'm not
exactly sure
about if
Jesus is
Lord.
Some of
you may
know that
have been
resisting.
If you
know that
you've
been resisting,
I'd say,
accept God's
offer.
Accept his
grace and
his mercy.
And if
you're not
sure,
that's okay
because we've
all been
not sure
at some
point in
our lives.
Those of us
who have
come to
faith in
Christ,
you're at
a place
where we've
all been.
But don't
stay there.
If there's
anything I
can do
is beg you
not to
stay there.
Keep
seeking
after God.
Ask him
to help
you.
Pray right
now in
your heart.
God,
help me.
Help me
to understand.
open my
eyes.
Help me
to come
to you.
If any
of you
guys have
questions
about any
of this
stuff,
please come
see me.
Please
come see
Ryan.
Come see
Michelle.
Grab any
of us.
We would
love to
talk to
you about
this.
God.
God,
thank you
for your
grace,
your love,
and your
mercy.
Thank you
for loving
us so
much that
you sent
your sinless
son to
guide and
replace.
God,
thank you
for the
grace that
you showed
us that
you did
deserve.
Thank you
for the
compassion
that you
showed us.
Help us,
God,
to be like
your son.
Help us to be
like Jesus.
Help us to
follow after
him.
Help us to
love one
another and
love you
well.
Thank you
for this
day,
God.
I pray
that your
spirit goes
out to
everyone that
is here
and change
his heart.